Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1319
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carey McWilliams papers
1894-1982
1921-1980
UCLA Library Special Collections
McWilliams, Carey
LSC.1319
40.0 Linear Feet (80 boxes and 11 oversize boxes)
Carey McWilliams (1905-1980) was a writer, lawyer, journalist, lecturer, activist, as well as Chief of the California Division of Immigration and Housing (1938-1942) and editor of The Nation (1955-1975). The collection contains personal diaries, scrapbooks, manuscripts, publicity materials, and assorted correspondence and research files related to McWilliams's life and career.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Iris McWilliams, 1982 and 1995.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922214223606533
Custodial History
The papers of Carey McWilliams do not survive as a whole in any one place. Both during his lifetime and after his death, parts of the papers were disposed of at various times by gift or sale. The Bancroft Library at the University of California, Berkeley, has custody of many of the manuscripts for his books and the UCLA Department of Special Collections has several collections in addition to Collection 1319 which were originally part of the McWilliams papers, the largest of which is Collection 1243 comprising research materials on farm labor in California and the problems of the Mexican American. This material was donated to the Library in 1952 as part of the John Randolph Haynes and Dora Haynes Foundation Collections. In addition, the major part of the following three groups of papers purchased by the Library in the 1950s, derived from McWilliams originally:
#278: Mary (Hunter) Austin collection. Correspondence, manuscripts, articles and clippings by and about Mary (Hunter) Austin. (ca. 150 pieces).
#277: Ambrose Bierce collection. Correspondence, pictures, clippings, notes, and other material by and about Bierce, assembled by McWilliams for his biography, Ambrose Bierce (New York, A.C. Boni, 1929). (ca. 500 items).
#276: George Serling collection. Correspondence, manuscripts, articles, clippings and ephemera by and about George Serling. (ca. 125 items).
Biography
Carey McWilliams was born December 13, 1905 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado. He completed his Juris Doctorate from the University of Southern California in 1927. From 1927-1938, McWilliams was an attorney at the law firm Black, Hammack in Los Angeles. In 1938, he was appointed as chief of Division of Immigration and Housing of the State of California, a position he kept until 1942. During the period from 1945-1955, he began his long association with The Nation, becoming successively contributing editor, associate editor, and then editorial director. From 1955-1975, he was The Nation's editor. In addition to his editorial duties, McWilliams was a prolific lecturer and writer, speaking on many subjects and contributing articles and essays to numerous publications. After his retirement from The Nation, he continued to write a regular column for that publication. His monographs include Ambrose Bierce, a biography (1929); Louis Adamic and shadow America (1935); Factories in the field: the story of migratory farm labor in California (1939); Ill fares the land: migrants and migratory labor in the United States (1942); Brothers under the skin (1943); Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, symbol of racial intolerance (1944); Southern California country: an island on the land (1946); A mask for privilege: anti-Semitism in America (1948); North from Mexico: the Spanish-speaking people of the United States (1949); California: the great exception (1949); Witch hunt: the revival of heresy (1950); and his autobiography The education of Carey McWilliams (1979). In the late 1970s, McWilliams was briefly a Regents Lecturer at the University of California Riverside and then taught one quarter at the University of California Los Angeles in the History Department. He died of cancer at the age of 74 on June 27, 1980 in New York, New York.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Carey McWilliams's bound volumes, manuscripts, publicity and criticism, printed materials, and assorted correspondence and research files related to his life, writings, publishing and lecture activities, and political causes. Files include personal diaries, scrapbooks, notebooks, handwritten and typed notes, press releases, leaflets, pamphlets, articles, clippings, professional and personal correspondence, and outlines and manuscript drafts. These files reflect McWilliams's varied professional interests, including racial minorities, migrant farm workers, civil liberties, the Cold War, McCarthyism, the press, American politics, literature, religious cults, and the West (notably California and Colorado). The manuscript series documents McWilliams's original work in different genres: addresses, articles, reviews, fiction, and monographs. The collection also contains materials related to McWilliams's tenure as the Chief of the California State Division of Immigration and Housing (DIH), and a copy of the file compiled on him by the Federal Bureau of Investigation.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Bound volumes, 1921-1980 (24.5 boxes)
Correspondence and research files, 1896-1982 (38 boxes)
Division of Immigration and Housing, 1939-1964 (1 box)
Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1940-1980 (1 box)
Lecture files, 1939-1980 (2 boxes)
Manuscripts, 1896-1981 (18 boxes)
The Nation, 1894-1980 (3 boxes)
Printed materials, 1925-1980 (1 box)
Publicity and criticism, 1929-1980 (1.5 boxes).
Related Material
Missing Title
Carey McWilliams papers, 1930-1940 (Collection 1243). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams correspondence, 1924-1975 (Collection 1356). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Collection of material about Carey McWilliams, 1925-1948 (Collection 2023). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Collection of materials by and about George Sterling, ca. 1901-1935 (Collection 276). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams collection of material about Ambrose Bierce, 1842-ca. 1914 (Collection 277). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams collection of material about Mary Hunter Austin, 1868-1934 (Collection 278). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams papers, 1921-1980 (Collection BANC MSS C-H 46). Available at Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.
Carey McWilliams miscellaneous papers, 1941-1945. Available at Hoover Institution Archives, Stanford, CA.
Honorable in all things oral history transcript: the memoirs of Carey McWilliams [oral history transcript] / Carey McWilliams, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1978. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
United States -- Race relations.; Migrant agricultural laborers -- California.; Mexican American migrant agricultural laborers -- California.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Diaries.; McWilliams, Carey -- Archives
- 1. Bound volumes, 1921-1980; 24.5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains assorted types of bound volumes. Arranged in subseries A-D as follows:
  A. Diaries, 1922-1980 (7.5 boxes)
  B. Financial ledgers, 1945-1980 (4 boxes)
  C. Notebooks, 1921-1972 (2 boxes)
  D. Scrapbooks, 1923-1949 (11 boxes).
  - 1A. Diaries, 1922-1980; 7.5 boxes
    This subseries contains McWilliams's personal diaries. A partial index is located at the beginning of the subseries. Preservation photocopies of the diaries from 1924, 1927, and 1929-33 are located in box 32. All other items are arranged in chronological order.
    - Loose notebook papers with index to diaries, ca. 1975; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Notebook contains a partial index to the diaries from the years 1945-1975, intermixed with a general index/timeline for contemporary events in "bound volumes" (unidentified) 1951-1974. Also contains miscellaneous notes and quotations, with subjects including: 1930s, 1940s, Legislative Investigation Report (1938 December 12), Dan Biderman, Clay Steinman, HUAC, Hamby, F.O. Matthiessen, Moynihan, Memo of Conversation Angus Cameron (1976 August 13), and book reviews.
    - Diary, 1922-1924; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Assorted diary entries and notes, both typed and handwritten. Includes reading lists, quotations and poems.
    - Diaries, 1923-1925; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      There is a preservation copy of the 1924 diary in box 32.
    - Diary, 1925-1927; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contains loose clippings and 2 loose leaves.
    - Diaries, 1926-1928; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1928 diary contains 2 black and white photographs, one of Betty Bond, the other unidentified. There is a preservation copy of the 1927 diary in box 32.
    - Diary, 1929-1933; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Contains 1 loose clipping. There is a preservation copy of this diary in box 32.
    - Diary, 1934-1937; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains 2 loose clippings.
    - Diaries, 1938-1939; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Diaries, 1940-1941; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Diaries, 1942-1943; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      1942 diary contains 1 loose clipping.
    - Diaries, 1944-1945; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      1944 diary contains 1 loose leaf.
    - Diaries, 1946-1947; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Diaries, 1948-1949; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      1948 diary contains 3 loose leaves.
    - Diaries, 1950-1951; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Diaries, 1954-1955; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Diaries, 1956-1957; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      1957 diary contains 2 loose clippings.
    - Diaries, 1958-1959; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      1958 diary contains 1 loose clipping and 2 loose leaves (In Remembrance of McWilliams's mother); 1959 diary contains 1 loose leaf (Memorial for Susan McWilliams).
    - Diaries, 1960-1961; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Both diaries contain 1 loose clipping.
    - Diaries, 1962-1963; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Diaries, 1964; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Diaries, 1965; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Diaries, 1966-1967; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      1966 diary contains 2 loose clippings.
    - Diaries, 1968-1969; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      1968 diary contains 1 loose clipping and 1 loose leaf; 1969 diary contains 1 loose leaf.
    - Diaries, 1970-1971; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      1970 diary contains 3 loose leaves.
    - Diaries, 1972-1973; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      1972 diary contains 1 loose clipping and 2 loose leaves.
    - Diaries, 1974-1975; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      1975 diary contains 2 loose leaves.
    - Diary, 1976; 1 item. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Diaries, 1977-1978; 2 items. (Box 11, Folder 1)
      1977 diary contains 1 loose clipping.
    - Diary, 1979; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Contains 8 loose clippings and 5 loose leaves.
    - Diary, 1980; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Contains 1 loose clipping and 1 loose leaf.
    - Diary--Preservation copy, 1924; 1 item. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Original is in box 1.
    - Diary--Preservation copy, 1927; 1 item. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Diary--Preservation copy, 1929-1933; 1 item. (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - 1B. Financial ledgers, 1945-1980; 4 boxes
    This subseries contains ledgers documenting McWilliams's personal and professional expenses. Items are arranged in chronological order.
    - Financial ledger, 1945-1947; 1 item. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Financial ledger, 1948-1950; 1 item. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Financial ledgers, 1951-1952; 2 items. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Financial ledger, 1953-1954; 1 item. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Financial ledger, 1955; 1 item. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Financial ledger, 1956; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Financial ledger, 1957; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Financial ledger, 1958; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Financial ledger, 1959; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Financial ledger, 1960; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Financial ledger, 1961; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Financial ledger, 1962; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Financial ledger, 1963; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Financial ledger, 1964; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Financial ledgers, 1965-1966; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Financial ledgers, 1967-1968; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Financial ledgers, 1969-1970; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Financial ledgers, 1970-1971; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Financial ledger, 1972; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Includes hospital patient ID card.
    - Financial ledger, 1973; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Financial ledgers, 1974-1975; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Financial ledgers, 1976; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Financial ledgers, 1977-1978; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Financial ledger, 1979; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Financial ledger, 1980; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1C. Notebooks, 1921-1972; 2 boxes
    This subseries contains notebooks of holograph and typewritten notes, reading lists, outlines, and quotations. It also includes a typewritten bibliography of McWilliams's published work from 1924-1972. Items are arranged in approximate chronological order.
    - Anti-Semitism, undated; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Handwritten notes and quotations dated 1878-1941.
    - Bibliography, 1922-1924, ca. 1972; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Typewritten bibliography of McWilliams's published works from 1924-1972; and a loose-leaf, handwritten reading list dated 1924.
    - Loose notebook leaves, 1921-1922, 1939-1940; 2 items. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Two groupings of loose notebook pages. First group consists of Division of Immigration and Housing appearances, a reading list, and typed notes on subjects including Nipomo, migratory schools, Korean residents of California, Filipinos, Imperial Valley, and agricultural strikes. Second group contains handwritten and typed reading lists and quotations.
    - General notebook (1 of 4), ca. 1930; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Extensive typed notes about and quotations from published articles (The Nation, The Outlook, Saturday Evening Post, etc.). Reviews and notes on books, principally titles on political and social science. Cover is illustrated with a clipping showing the view of Los Angeles from a hill garden.
    - General notebook (2 of 4), ca. 1939; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Handwritten notes and quotations dated from 1889-1936. The primary subject is Southern California. Also contains loose leaves and many blank pages.
    - General notebook (3 of 4), ca. 1941; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Handwritten notes and quotations dated from 1904-1941. Subjects include the Philippines, Puerto Rico, and racism against the Chinese.
    - General notebook (4 of 4), undated; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Handwritten notes and quotations with references to 1871-1899. Subjects include the Spanish-American War and Ambrose Bierce.
    - Quotations (1 of 2), ca. 1931; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Handwritten quotations from New Republic, The Nation and other publications dated 1886-1931.
    - Quotations (2 of 2), undated; 2 items. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Typed notes and clippings of quotations in alphabetical order by person, and handwritten notes. Labeled "Quotes from writers" on cover.
    - Minorities and race in America, ca. 1940-1949; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Typed notes, quotations, and outlines. Primary subject is racism, including African Americans, Japanese-Americans, and the South. Titles of outlines include "Race relations in tomorrow's America," "Reaction to Smith vs. Allright," "A practical solution for America's race problem," "Orientals in American life," and "Japanese-Americans face the future," among others. Also includes notes from an interview with Jacob Kravitz of the Jewish Welfare Federation in Dallas, dated 1946 March 30.
    - Idea notebook, undated; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Five pages of handwritten notes.
  - 1D. Scrapbooks, 1923-1949; 11 boxes
    This subseries contains scrapbooks of clippings from a variety of publications, many mentioning McWilliams or his work. Some scrapbooks also include clippings of articles and essays written by him. Items are arranged by the original scrapbook number assigned to each volume by McWilliams himself.
    - Scrapbook I, 1939-1940; 1 item. (Box 56, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings that mention Factories in the Field. Clippings come from numerous publications, mostly newspapers, including some from The Nation and a few written by McWilliams. Other subjects include migrant labor, Grapes of Wrath, and books. Ca. 60 pages.
    - Scrapbook II, 1939; 1 item. (Box 56, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications (mostly newspapers) that mention Factories in the Field. Other subjects include migrant labor, Grapes of Wrath, and books. Ca. 70 pages.
    - Scrapbook III, 1945-1946; 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 1)
      Contains primarily clippings and some assorted printed materials. Majority of clippings by or about McWilliams and/or his work. Clippings come from numerous publications, mostly newspapers (including a few from The Nation and PM). Subjects include While You Were Gone, Prejudice: Japanese Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance, Primer for White Folks. Ca. 30 pages.
    - Scrapbook IV, 1935-1936; 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 2)
      Contains primarily clippings and some assorted printed materials. Majority of clippings by or about McWilliams and/or his work. Clippings come from numerous publications, mostly newspapers, a few from The Nation and Pacific Weekly. Subjects include Louis Adamic, fascism, "yellow peril," anti-Semitism, the press. Ca. 50 pages.
    - Scrapbook V, 1939-1940; 1 item. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      Contains primarily newspaper clippings. Majority of clippings mention McWilliams's work as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing. Clippings come from numerous publications, including 2 loose leaf articles from NM. Subjects include farm labor, migrant labor, Factories in the Field, Grapes of Wrath, and the Bancroft Debates. Ca. 70 pages.
    - Scrapbook VI, 1938-1944; 1 item. (Box 58, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings and some assorted printed materials. Majority of clippings mention McWilliams or his work. Clippings come from numerous publications, mostly newspapers. Subjects include farm labor, migrant labor, Factories in the Field (reviews), race relations, aliens, Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, Humphrey Cobb, Wage Rate Hearings. Ca. 90 pages.
    - Scrapbook VII, 1935-1938; 1 item. (Box 59, Folder 1)
      Contains newspaper clippings from numerous publications. Subjects are farm and migratory labor, and the Orange County strikes. Ca. 50 pages.
    - Scrapbook VIII, 1942-1943; 1 item. (Box 59, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings, from numerous publications, of reviews of Ill Fares the Land. Many loose clippings in addition to scrapbook's ca. 40 pages.
    - Scrapbook IX, 1939-1940; 1 item. (Box 60, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications (mostly newspapers) and a few assorted printed materials. These clippings mention McWilliams's work as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing and/or as author of Factories in the Field. Subjects are primarily farm and migratory labor and housing. Contains 2 loose leaves in addition to scrapbook's ca. 60 pages.
    - Scrapbook X, 1944-1945; 1 item. (Box 60, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications, mostly reviews of (or articles touching on the issues of) Prejudice: Japanese Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance. Also includes a few articles written by McWilliams for NM and The Nation. Ca. 70 pages.
    - Scrapbook XII, 1923-1931, 1937; 1 item. (Box 61, Folder 1)
      Contains primarily clippings from numerous publications and some assorted printed materials, including an attestation of McWilliams's membership in The Order of the Coif (a national honor society). Main subjects are George Sterling, and the New Regionalism. Also contains typewritten poetry manuscripts by Sterling, clippings of published poems and literary articles and reviews by McWilliams. Contains loose leaves in addition to scrapbook's ca. 50 pages.
    - Scrapbook XIII, 1935-1938; 1 item. (Box 61, Folder 2)
      Contains newspaper clippings from numerous publications. Main subject is labor, including farm labor and wages. Ca. 50 pages.
    - Scrapbook XIV, 1939; 1 item. (Box 62, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications (mostly newspapers) that mention Factories in the Field. Other subjects include migrant labor, Grapes of Wrath, and books. Ca. 50 pages
    - [Scrapbook XXI], 1946-1949; 1 item. (Box 62, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications of reviews of Southern California Country. Includes 3 manuscripts of reviews (2 by George Stiller, 1 by Lawrence Clark Powell). Contains additional loose clippings (2 envelopes). Ca. 60 pages.
    - Scrapbook XVI, 1933-1935; 1 item. (Box 63, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings, including many articles written by McWilliams for California Curiosa, Tides West, New Republic and other publications. Subjects include Ambrose Bierce, California, and elections. Ca. 70 pages.
    - Scrapbook XVII, 1925-1932; 1 item. (Box 63, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings, primarily literary reviews by McWilliams for numerous publications. Also contains loose leaves in addition to scrapbook's ca. 80 pages.
    - Scrapbook XV, 1933-1937; 1 item. (Box 64, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings, some assorted printed materials, and 2 loose leaves (1 from a manuscript about a journalist White). McWilliams wrote many of these articles, which appeared in numerous publications including American Mercury, Pacific Weekly, The Nation, News of the World. Subjects include Ambrose Bierce, farm labor, Nazis, Fascism, and the Congress of Western Writers. Ca. 50 pages.
    - Scrapbook XIX, 1940; 1 item. (Box 64, Folder 2)
      Contains primarily newspaper clippings from numerous publications. Majority of clippings mention McWilliams's work as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing. Subjects include farm labor, migrant labor and housing, Factories in the Field, and George Kidwell's statements. Ca. 60 pages.
    - Scrapbook XI, 1943; 1 item. (Box 75, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications. Most are reviews of Brother Under the Skin, but a few address the Zoot Suit Riots. Also includes a list of newspaper and magazine advertising on McWilliams. Contains a few loose leaves in addition to scrapbook's ca. 40 pages.
    - Scrapbook XVIII, 1939-1945; 1 item. (Box 75, Folder 2)
      Contains clippings from numerous publications and some assorted printed materials, including a few articles written by McWilliams for The New Republic and The Nation. Many clippings mention McWilliams's work as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing. Subjects include Prejudice: Japanese Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance, Ill Fares the Land, farm labor, and housing. Ca. 80 pages.
    - [Scrapbook XX], 1945; 1 item. (Box 76, Folder 1)
      Contains clippings/reviews of Ill Fares the Land from British and Irish newspapers. 8 pages.
- 2. Correspondence and research files, 1896-1982; 38 boxes
  This series contains McWilliams's general correspondence and research files, and comprises the bulk of the collection. Arranged in subseries A-D as follows:
  A. Files on people, 1912-1982 (11 boxes)
  B. Files on subjects, 1914-1982 (20 boxes)
  C. General correspondence, 1923-1980 (6 boxes)
  D. Publisher correspondence, 1942-1980 (1 box).
  - 2A. Files on people, 1912-1982; 11 boxes